<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise of the nature and vse of things indifferent Tendinge to proue, that the ceremonies in present controuersie amongst the ministers of the gospell in the realme of Englande, are neither in nature nor vse indifferent.</title>
            <author>Bradshaw, William, 1571-1618.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1605</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16623</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3530</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106384</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842101</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842101</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6727</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16623)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6727)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 627:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise of the nature and vse of things indifferent Tendinge to proue, that the ceremonies in present controuersie amongst the ministers of the gospell in the realme of Englande, are neither in nature nor vse indifferent.</title>
                  <author>Bradshaw, William, 1571-1618.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by W. Jones' secret press],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London?] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1605.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By William Bradshaw.</note>
                  <note>Printer identified by STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Liturgy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Adiaphora --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6727:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6727:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TREATISE <hi>OF THE NATVRE AND VSE OF THINGS INDIF<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FERENT.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>TENDINGE TO PROVE, THAT THE CEREMONIES <hi>IN PRESENT CONTROVER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie</hi> Amongſt the miniſters of the <hi>goſpell in the Realme of England, are</hi> neither in nature or vſe Indifferent.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 18.23.</bibl>
               <p>IF I haue ſpoken euell beare witneſſe of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell, but If I haue spoken well why ſmiteſt thou mee.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 5.<hi>11.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Bleſſed are yee when men reuil you and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cut you &amp; ſay all manner of euel againſt you for my ſake falſly, Reioyce and be glad for great is your reward in heauen for so perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted they the prophets that were before you.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed <hi>1605.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:6727:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE PRINTER TO THE Reader.</head>
            <p>A Copy of this Treatiſſe by the proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming into my hand: I thought it behoofull for my Countrimen, that they ſhould be made acquainted with it, that by meanes thereof they might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue ſom lyght of the truth for which ſo many ſuffer. The author whoſoeuer hee is hath litle cauſe to be offended with it, The paines he hath taken in it, doth perſwad me that he cannot but deſier the ſame in it ſelf though daunger &amp; want of meanes might hinder him from publiſhing it, But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer (good reader) accept it as a teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of my vowes for the good of my Countrey, the weale whereof ſhall euer poſſeſſe me, though I cannot poſſeſſe it.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:6727:2"/>
            <head>A TREATISE OF THINGES <hi>Indifferent.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. 1.</hi> Of thinges Indifferent ingenerall.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A</hi> Thing Indifferent (in the largeſt extent of ſence) is any <hi>Mean</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween two <hi>Extreames.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Extreames</hi> (properly) are the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vttermoſt bounds and limitts of any thing being in direct oppoſition one vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the other.</p>
               <p n="3">3 To be a <hi>Mean</hi> between two <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treames,</hi> is ſo to be ſeated between the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as that it ſtand equally affected to ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, inclinnyng no more to the one, then to the other.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Hence the Latins call: things indiffe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, <hi>Res mediae.</hi> (Midle matters) And that by reaſon of that analogie &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion that is between them, &amp; thoſe things that in phiſicall or Mathemati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Dimenſions poſſeſſe the midle place in any line, figure or bodie: For, that is properly called the midle of any thing,
<pb facs="tcp:6727:3"/> that in poſition being as neere as can be, to both extrea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es, inclineth no more to the one then to the other, but is a like equally diſtant from both.</p>
               <p n="5">5 And they are therfore called, <hi>things indifferent,</hi> becauſe in their relation to thoſe extreames between which they are ſeated, and vnto which they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, they ſtand indifferently diſpoſed and affected to either, whence of the <hi>Greeks</hi> they are called <hi>Adiaphora,</hi> vnto which our Engliſh terme doth pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciſly anſwere. For as that is iuſt the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of a line that leaueth on both ſids ſo much to either extreame, that there is in reſpect of it no difference between the one and the other: but vnto, it both are equall &amp; a like: So thoſe things are called <hi>indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</hi> properly, that without any difference, doe equally agree vnto, or diſſent, from thoſe extreames, vnto which they haue reference &amp; relation.</p>
               <p n="6">6 By all this it may appeare that things Indifferent, are not ſuch, ſimply, in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:6727:3"/> &amp; of themſelues conſidered, but as they are compared, and haue relatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the ſaide oppoſite extreames, as the Center in a circle, conſidered in it ſelfe, and by it ſelfe, is not the midle of any thing, but only as it hath reference to the oppoſite extreames in the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference: from any of which it is equally diſtant, and in that reſpect only is it cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led the <hi>mean</hi> or midle of ſuch a figure.</p>
               <p n="7">7 The very eſſence therefore of a thing <hi>indifferent,</hi> conſiſts in that equall and indifferent reference and relation that it hath to ſome two oppoſite terms or ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>treames, vnto which either in ſence or reaſon it is compared, and by which on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye it is meaſured. So that it is in the number of thoſe things that in ſchooles are called relatiues, all which haue only but an accidentall being. The ſubiects therof being variable, according to the diuers references and reſpects that they haue vnto diuers things. For as a man ſimply conſidered in himſelfe, is nether
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:6727:4"/> huſband, Father, nor Maſter, but onely in reſpect of Wife, Child and Seruant. And as the ſame man in diuers reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects may be a father &amp; a ſonne, a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and a ſeruant: So nothing is in &amp; of it ſelfe indifferent, but only in relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on &amp; reference to ſome oppoſit extrea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: And thoſe thinges which in ſome ſuch reſpect may be indifferent, in ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reſpect may be Extreames.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Cap. 2.</hi> Of things more commonly called Indifferent.</head>
               <p n="1">1 Though <hi>things indifferent</hi> may in that former generalitie, ſpread them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to any mediocritie whatſoeuer. Yet Cuſtome the miſtris of all ſpeach, and language, hath reſtrained &amp; limit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted the name, to ſuch things only, as are a <hi>Mean</hi> between good and euell. So that (to omitt what in rigorous proprietie of ſpeach may be comprehended vnder the name that is giuen vnto them) In commen vſe of ſpeach, a thing indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:6727:4"/> is onely, any mediocritie, between good and evell.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The proper Extreames therefore of things indifferent, being good &amp; euell, they cannot (retaininge the nature of their indifference) communicate or per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>take of either, for whatſoeuer ſtandeth equally affected to good and evell, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not in that affection, haue in it, either good or evell: It being imposſible, that either of the extreames ſhould be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in the <hi>Mean,</hi> without diſtruction of the nature thereof.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Whatſoeuer then voyde of all euell,<note n="(a)" place="margin">ſuch they ſay are our Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies. For thoſe things are good that are decent, orderly: &amp; mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es of edification.</note> participateth but the leaſt meaſure of good: or voyde of all good, pertaketh but the<note n="b)" place="margin">Such wee ſay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and haue proued the Ceremonies to be.</note> leaſt degree of evell, cannot beare the name of a thing <hi>indifferent,</hi> For there can be noe indifferencie in that, which inclinneth more to the one extreame, then to the other.</p>
               <p n="4">4 A thing indifferent therfore being a <hi>mean,</hi> between good &amp; evell, it is<note place="margin">So are not theſe ceremonies</note> ſo ſeated between them: that it is as far
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:6727:5"/> remooued from Good, as a thinge not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, can be, and as far remoued from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, as a thing not Good can be, and as neare vnto Good and evill, as any thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g can be, that is neither good nor euill. So that whatſoever is Indifferent, is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good nor evill, whatſoeuer is either good or euill, is not Indifferent, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is not Indifferent is either good or evill.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Things <hi>indifferent,</hi> being equally devided from good &amp; evill, are in like manner, deuided from all the properties of either, For euery propertie being vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeperable from that ſubiect, from the na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture whereof it ſpringeth, noe one, can be communicated to any thing but vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that, vnto which the ſubiect it ſelfe communicateth it ſelfe, Yf therfore the propertie of any extreame, be found in a thing indifferent, the extrea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e it ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lfe: is to be ſound likewiſe therein. Which to imagin, is as abſurd, as to looke to find the Circumference of a Circle in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:6727:5"/> the Center.</p>
               <p n="6">6 No indifferent thing therefore as it is an indifferent thing,<note n="d" place="margin">But they ſay that the Ceremonies in controuerſie haue: For that which is a grace and ornament to Good, maketh the better.</note> hath power to make any thing good or evill, better or worſe: For it is the property only of good &amp; evill, either to make or increaſe good or evill in any thing.</p>
               <p n="7">7 That<note n="e" place="margin">But ſuch are the ceremonies inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trouerſie.</note> which doth more hurt or good, then ſome things that are good or euell, is not indifferent, but either good or evill: for nothing but Good, can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in goodnes that which is good, and nothing but evill, can exceed in hurt, that which is evil.</p>
               <p n="8">8 Whatſoeuer<note n="f" place="margin">This doe the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie:</note> worketh vpon any af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of man, ſtirring vp in him, loue, hatred, delight, ſorrow, zaele, mallice, envie, Ielouſie, hope, feare &amp;c. cannot be apprehended as a thing indifferent, by him in whom theſe pasſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s are wrought. For it is the propertie only of thoſe thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs that preſent themſelues as good or evil, to begett and moue ſuch pasſions in the ſoule of man. For it is imposſible that a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:6727:6"/> thing indifferent apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded as a thing indifferent, ſhould beget any thinge in the ſoule of man but Indifferencie, and a Stoicall apathie or ſenceleſnes: So that whatſoeuer a<note n="g" place="margin">As our Prelates doe the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nies</note> man intirely loueth &amp; delighteth in, admireth, commendeth, perſueth with zeale, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth with authoritie. Whatſoeuer alſo a man ſhall abhorre, condeme, forbid, puniſh, perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute, he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not in any ſinceritie affirme, that he iudgeth that thing to be indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, but to be in ſome degree either good or evell.</p>
               <p n="9">9 The omisſion of that is indifferent, the commisſion whereof is indifferent: and that whoſe<note n="h" place="margin">Such is the omiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion of our cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es ſaid to be and that in a high degree.</note> omisſion is evel, is certainly good.</p>
               <p n="10">10 All the former premiſes conſidered this muſt needes follow. That<note n="I" place="margin">To commaund our ceremonies, is to commaund as the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſaye, a great good yea, a publicke com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good.</note> to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund a thing indifferent is to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d noe good, to for bid a thing indifferent, is to forbid noe evell.<note n="k" place="margin">But to vſe the ce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>remonies is to doe much good, if they edifie the ſoule.</note> To doe a thing indifferent is to doe no good. To forbeare a thing indifferent<note n="l" place="margin">None are more ſpitfully intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted then thoſe that forbeare theſe ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſure their in they doe much euell:</note> is to doe no evell.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:6727:6"/> And therefore to puniſh for a thing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, is to puniſh for no evell.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Cap. 3.</hi> Of thinges indifferent in ſpeciall.</head>
               <p n="1">1 The eſſence of things <hi>indifferent,</hi> conſiſting in a meere and equall priua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Good and Evell, there cannot be giuen any true kindes or degrees of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, For all priuattiues conſidered in them ſelues are of the ſame nature.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Though their be no true kindes of them, yet they may be varied according to the diuerſitie of thoſe extreames with which they are compared. And therefore may be diſtinguiſhed accordinge to the commen diſtinctions of good and evell.</p>
               <p n="3">3 That Good that hath not an Evell oppoſite vnto it in the ſame kinde, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be the extreame of any thing <hi>indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent,</hi> &amp; therfore cannot varie, diſtin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>guiſh, or denominat a thing indifferent. as if their be not an oppoſit colour vnto white, then it is imposſible to imagine: how white ſhould be an extreame, to any
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:6727:7"/> other colour, or any other colour a mean vnto it.</p>
               <p n="4">4 That which is properly a mean, muſt agree with the extreames in althinges in which the extreames doe agree: for example, If blacke and white be both of them colours: that which is properlie a mean between blacke and white, muſt be a colour alſo, for it were abſurd to call any thing but a colour, a mean between blacke and white: ſo that the mean fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes the common natures &amp; qualities of both the extreames, for as it is ſaide before, That only is a mean that is not only equally diſtant from two extrea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es, but withall is as neere to both as may be, which cannot be verified of that mean that ſhall not be found to agree with the extreams in thoſe things wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the extreames doe agree within them ſelues, and therefore things indifferent follow their extreames. As therfore that cannot be an extreame that hath not in the ſame kind an oppoſite, ſo that can be
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:6727:7"/> no <hi>medium</hi> to any extreams, that doth diſſent from them in that wherein they ſhall accord and agree. So that that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination and predication that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longes to both extreames, belongs alſo to their <hi>mean.</hi> The mean between two op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite Qualities is a Qualitie: betweene two ſubſtances, a ſubſtance, between two actions, an Action: between two goods, a Good, betwee<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> two evills, an Euil, betwen two quantities, a quantitie &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Hence it will followe, that no<note n="a" place="margin">All ſubſtances therefore are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different only by accident, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of ſome vſe</note> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance (as it is a ſubſtance) can be called thing indifferent, becauſe that ther is a no ſubſtance that is evill as it is a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. For an indifferent ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, muſt needs (if ther were any ſuch) be a mean between a good and an evill ſubſtance. Yf then there be no evill ſubſtaunces, it cannot be imagined how there ſhould be any indifferent.</p>
               <p n="6">6 The like may be ſaide of all<note n="b" place="margin">As alſo of all ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificiall which imitate natures.</note> crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſpecies and kindes of things coſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not only in their ſubſtances, but qua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lities
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:6727:8"/> and diſpoſitions. For the voyce of God pronouncynge them all to be good: none of them are evell, and if none of them be evell, none are indifferent. For indifferent created things, can haue no place: either reall, or imaginatiue, but between a created Good: and a created Evell. There is therefore no Creature of God: nor noe created propertie or quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of any creature: that is by creation a Thing Indifferent.</p>
               <p n="7">7 Alſo vpon the ſaid grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds it apperes, that there is noe<note n="B" place="margin">And therefore there cannot be made an abſolut and perpetuall law concerning any thing vnder the name of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, for a law bindeth on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye to good and puniſheth for e<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uell, and therfore to imagine a law that bindeth to the doinge of a thing indifferent when that thing indifferent turns evel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> as the moſt indifferent thing may, then the force of the law ceaſeth.</note> abſolute <hi>Indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent thing:</hi> becauſe their is no thing in nature either abſolutly good, or ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutly evell: It being imposſible that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thinge ſhould be an abſolute <hi>Mean,</hi> whoſe extreames are not abſolute, for where one extreame is abſolute and the other not abſolute: the Mean cannot be abſolute, for if it be, it enclineth more to one extreame then the other, which is to diſtroye the nature of a thinge in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:6727:8"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. 4.</hi> Of the firſt diſtinction of things indifferent.</head>
               <p n="1">1 Things indifferent therefore, being to be diſtinguiſhed according to thoſe diſtinctions of Good and Evell that are equally commen to them both, we are in the next place diſtinctly to propounde the ſame, and by them accordingly to diſtinguiſh the other.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Firſt therfore Good &amp; Euell is ſuch, either in appearance onely, or indeed al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. Whence arriſeth the firſt diſtinction of <hi>things indiferent,</hi> for accordinglie ſome thinges are indifferent in appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce onely, ſome indeed.</p>
               <p n="3">3 A Thing indifferet in appearaunce onely, is that which is a <hi>mean</hi> betweene that Good and Euell<note n="a" place="margin">co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider whether the miſticall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ts of an Id<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>latrous religion &amp; wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, be not at leaſt an evell in appearaunce &amp; ſheew, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot be ſo much as in ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pea aunce indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent.</note> that is in ſheew and appearance onely. For that appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to be indifferent, that being Good or euell indeed, appeareth or ſeemeth to be neither.</p>
               <p n="4">4 A thing indifferent indeed: is that which is a Mean between thoſe thinges
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:6727:9"/> that are in truth and veritie Good or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell. So that ſuch an indifferent is voyde of all true good,<note n="b" place="margin">If our Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies were ſuch. The Deuill and Antich ſt &amp; all ſuperſtitious and lewd perſons would not ſo much dote vpon them, and the h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tes of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny learned and godly men wold not burn againſt them as they doe</note> and evill.</p>
               <p n="5">5 As that which is good in appearau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce onely, is indeed either euill or indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, and that which is evell in appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce only, is indeed either good or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, and that which is indifferent in appearau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce only, is indeed either good or evill, So that which is indifferent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, is in truth, neither good nor euill.</p>
               <p n="6">6 As<note n="c" place="margin">If Turciſme, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daiſme. Pag <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt Idolatrye that euer was a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mongſt the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then were eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſhed by that lawe and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie that theſe Ceremonies are, any poynt or per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cell therof might bee mainetained by the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>me or the like g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds. That M. Hooker Couel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lkes, mainetaine the Indifferencie of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>es ceremonies And their is noe Arti. of faith and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ligion, but (by the ſame method that the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>veo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> vſeth againſt the Diſcipl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reformed Churche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>) it may be traduced and oppug<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> moſt odious gro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe, and impious.</note> the groſſeſt evill may by mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es of ſome counterfeit or ſhadow caſt vpon it, be in appearaunce, the greateſt good, and the greateſt good may be diſguiſed, and in ſheew transformed into the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt evill: So with much more facilitie may either of them by the wit of man haue caſt vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the formes of things indifferent.</p>
               <p>So that there muſt be ſpeciall heed taken that we admitt not of all things as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different indeed that preſent themſelues to vs vnder that name and ſhape: Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentines
<pb facs="tcp:6727:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> can diſguiſe &amp; collor any thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g. and it is now a dayes the common excer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciſe of the greateſt wittes of the world. to tranſforme good into Euill, Euill into good, and both into Indifferent ſo that in theſe dayes ſcant any thing is as it appeares or appeares as it is.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Cap. 5.</hi> The 2 diſtinction of things Indifferent</head>
               <p n="1">1 Good and Euill is eyther<note place="margin">Some of our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Divins think all external things Indifferent: which ſheews that they that talke moſt o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> them, know leſt what they are.</note> 
                  <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall</hi> or <hi>Externall,</hi> accordinge to which difference ariſeth a ſecond deſtin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ction of <hi>Things Indifferent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 An Externall Indifferent is whatſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>euer hath in it nether inward good nor<note n="b" place="margin">What inward hurt and evill is in theſe Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nies they beſt know, that are beſt acquainted with the ſtate of their flocke.</note> Euill</p>
               <p n="3">3 An <hi>Internall Indifferent,</hi> is whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer hath in it, neither inward <hi>good</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">What inward hurt and evill is in theſe Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nies they beſt know, that are beſt acquainted with the ſtate of their flocke.</note> nor <hi>evill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4 Something<note n="c" place="margin">The Doctor of Oxford aske what hurt can a wiſe man ſee in a ſquare Cap &amp; a ſurplice. Inded their is no out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde hurt or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill in it, but it muſt be conſide<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red wether their be not any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward hurt their<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, for if it can be proued that by them, the ſoules of many are poy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoned with ſuper<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtitious conceits then it is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent that they haue inwarde hurt in them.</note> Externall Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent may haue in it internall good or E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill &amp; ſomethinges internally Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent may haue in them outward Good
<pb facs="tcp:6727:10"/> or Euill</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. 6.</hi> OF the 3. diſtinction of things Indifferent.</head>
               <p n="1">1 Thirdly Good and Euill, is either of it ſelf or by accident: which alſo make the 3 diſtinction of things Indifferent.</p>
               <p n="2">2 An Indifferent by accident is a meane between thoſe Extreames that<note n="a" place="margin">If it can be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued that theſe Ceremonies are but evill by acci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dent, (they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not good of themſelues) it is enough to argue that they are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill and not indif<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ferent. For if ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things that are good in them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelues, be to bee for borne, when by ſome acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent they doe hurt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> much more ought a thing in different when it hurteth, though but by accident</note> are Good and Euill by accident and not of themſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lues: for that muſt needs be only accidentally indifferent, whoſe Extrea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es (by which it is limited and defined) are but accidentallie good or Euill: ſo that whatſoeuer is Indifferent onely in relati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of ſome accidentall good or Euill is Indifferent not of it ſelſe but by accident</p>
               <p n="4">4<note n="b" place="margin">Ergo their is no thing abſolutely Indifferent (as our Divines of ſtate drea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e) but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y ſome circum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtaunce of time, place, perſon, vſe: it may be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y good, or very evill.</note> There is nothing ſo good of it ſelfe, but it may be made Euill by acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, nothing ſo euill of it ſelf but it may become good by accident. Nothing ſo good or Euil but it may become Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent by accident, nothing ſo Indifferent of it ſelfe but it may become Good or
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:6727:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> Euill by accident.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Vnto this head may be referred, ſuch things as are Indifferent by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon for as ther are ſome things good ſimplie that are Euill in compariſon. &amp; ſomethings Euill ſimplie that are good in compariſon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo alſo there is ſome good and Euill, that in compariſon with others is Indifferent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Cap. 7.</hi> OF a 4. Deſtinction. of things Indifferent.</head>
               <p n="8">8 THings are Good or Evill either <hi>Actually</hi> or <hi>Potentially.</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">A poſſibilitie of evill in a thinge indifferent, mak<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth it evill and worthy to be re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>moued Nature teacheth to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent evills, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> a man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not doe in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention thereof, then to leaue of a thing in it ſelfe indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t which doth no good &amp; may doe hurt.</note> So are alſo Things Indifferent.</p>
               <p n="2">2 A thing actually <hi>Indifferent,</hi> is that which hath in it neither actuall good nor hurt.</p>
               <p n="3">3 A Thing <hi>Potentially Indifferent,</hi> is that which in act doth either hurt or good, though in po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſibilitie it may doe neither.</p>
               <p n="4">4 There is nothing actually Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent but is potentially good or (a) euill,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:6727:11"/> Their is nothing potentially, onely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different but it is actually either good or euill. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rfore their is nothing abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutly Indifferent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. 8.</hi> OF the <hi>5.</hi> Diſtinction of things Indifferent.</head>
               <p n="1">1 LAſtly, Good and evill is either Corporall in reſpect of the body, or ſpirituall, in r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſpect of the minde, In which reſpect, Things Indifferent doe alwayes vary.</p>
               <p n="2">2 A Thinge Indifferent in reſpect of the bodie is any ſuch thing that applyed to the bodie, doth it neither good nor hurt. As that which maketh a man nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther rich nor poore, Strong nor Weake, bewtifull nor deformed, hungrie nor yet ſatisfied, ſicke: nor healthy. &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="3">3 That may be Good<note n="a" place="margin">Circumſtaunces of time &amp; place doe alſo v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ry the things of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s kinde exceeding<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly. For that in ſome tyme and ſome place is in different to ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e bodie, that in an other place, and at another tyme is Good or euill.</note> to the bodie in one reſpect that is evill in another et con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tra and that may be indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto it, in one reſpect, that is good or euill in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other. Alſo that may be good or evill to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:6727:11"/> one part of the bodie that is indifferent to another parte. And a thing may be indifferent to one, that is good or evill to another.</p>
               <p n="4">4 A thing Indifferent in reſpect of the <hi>minde</hi> or Soule, is whatſoeuer hauinge reference and relation to the ſoule<note n="b" place="margin">Either indeed or appearaunce of it ſelfe or acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent: actually or potentially.</note> doth it neither good nor hurt.</p>
               <p n="5">5 The Goods and Evills of ſoule: are either diſpoſitions, qualities, or habitsin the ſoule, or ſuch actions as proceed from them. As Thoughts, words, deeds. All which are called Morall. A <hi>Morall good:</hi> is whatſoeuer in Man or from man is agreable and correſpondent to the law of Nature, Reaſon, or the Diui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e Law of God revealed ſupernaturally in his word. Vnto this head are to be refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: all true wiſdome, knowledge, vnder ſtanding, prouidence, diſcretion, and all actions flowyng from the ſame. Alſo all Morall virtues, as, Iuſtice, Temptera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, Holines, &amp;c. With all the Actions pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedyng from them. All which are ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:6727:12"/> and ruled by ſome or other of the former Lawes. A Morall Evill is what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is any wayes repugnau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t (whether in generall or perticular) to any of thos former Lawes. As Ignorance, Folly, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtice, intemperaunce &amp;c. with all Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions proceedyng from them.</p>
               <p n="6">6 Thoſe things are in a Morall reſpect indifferant (whether they be Qualities, inclinations, Habitts or Actions) That haue in them (b) neither <hi>vertue nor vice.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">See ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p. 8. ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ct <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap>gent.</note> Herein ſuch Actions of mans will are moſt frequent, that are neither com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded nor forbidden in the word of God.</p>
               <p n="7">7 Ther is no Action of mans will: ſo indifferent<note n="c" place="margin">So that (by M. Hookers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>auor) a man may by takynge vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> or a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſh. commit a Moral vice<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple if he ſhoulde vſe to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e it in the time of p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> but the doing thereof (by ſome circumſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce) may be repugnaunt to the lawe of God and by conſequent be hurt full to the ſoule of man.</p>
               <p n="8">8 An Action that in ſome one reſpect vnto ſome one ſpeciall lawe, is Indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in reſpect of ſome other lawe may bee Good or Evill. As that action may be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:6727:12"/> Religious or Superſtitious, that hath in it neither Temperancie nor In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperancie.</p>
               <p n="9">9 Any action done by man that is not commaunded<note n="*" place="margin">Such are the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies in con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trouerſie: They are no where in generall or ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>all commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, no more then the ſhave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> crown and holy water, &amp; yet<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they haue been and are the ſpeciall meanes and occaſion of the Sciſme of many hundred Browniſts Of much ſuperſtion in many 1000. ignorant prore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, &amp; of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny infinits of wil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full, Papiſtes in their Idolatry, as is moſt evident. Alſo (yf it be a ſinne to diſlike our Lords ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall) there is no one greater caus that moveth thoſe that the profane call Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritanes to doe it, then theſe Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, which if they might be freed from, as all other re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ormed Churches are. There is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Ciuill obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience or ſubiection due vnto them: that they woulde refuſe to performe, in as a lowe a degree as any other whatſoeuer.</note> by God, either expreſly or by direct conſequent, that is a meanes either of it ſelfe or by accident of any hurt either to the bodie, or ſoule, of a mans ſelfe, or of his Neighbour, either by bringing evill into them, or nuriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng or increaſing evill in them, cannot beare the name of an Indifferent action For there is no indifferencie in that, which being not required of God. (and therefore is not Good) doth hurt (any wayes) a man: which muſt needs be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the lawe of God. For the ſome of the Lawe of God being the loue of God and our Neighbour, And Loue ai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming onely at the Good of the loued. That ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that (beſids the law) doth any hurt to any, muſt either haue an exceeption in the lawe, or elſe be againſt it, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it cannot be indifferent.</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:6727:13"/>10 Morall Actions whether virtues or vices, reſpect either God imediately, or our ſelues or our Neighbour, as is inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated before. So doe alſo all Indifferent Actions.</p>
               <p n="11">11 That Action is indifferent in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of God, that doth neither advance nor obſcure the glorie of God. For this is the onely Good or Evill we can doe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God.</p>
               <p n="12">12 Ther is no Action that a man can doe by the power of his will, but either in it ſelfe or by accident, it doth either glorifie or diſhonor God, and therefore no action in reſpect of God, is merely &amp; abſolutly indifferent,<note n="c" place="margin">Such are the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies and rites that are peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arly acted in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine worſhip, if they be good &amp; lawfull.</note> but thereby God receaueth ſome Honor or diſhonor.</p>
               <p n="13">13 All Actions of Religion (amongſt which<note n="a" place="margin">What honor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaueth God by our ceremonies? It is certaine that Antichriſt receaueth great honor by them.</note> thoſe are ſpeciall that are pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiarly done in Divine ſeruice) are (if they be as they ought to be) in a ſpeciall manner good, tending more directly to the glory of God, then any other Actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>refore no action of Religion, whether
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:6727:13"/> it be Morall or Ceremoniall, is indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent but either good or evill.</p>
               <p n="14">14 No Action of Religion whether Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall or Ceremoniall<note n="(b)" place="margin">Such are our Ceremonies elſe they are not In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different.</note> grounded onely vpon the will of man, and not vpon the worde of God, can bring any ſpeciall glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry to God, and therefore no ſuch Act can be an act of Religion, but of ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, and therefore cannot be indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent.</p>
               <p n="15">15 Ther being ſome myſticall Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of Religion Good: and ſome Evill. If ther be any myſticall Ceremonies in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, they muſt then in ſome ſpeciall and materiall poynt differ from the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, even as far as from the good. But there is no myſticall Rite of religion,<note n="(c)" place="margin">Crosſing in Baptiſme beinge no more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded nor no leſſe forbidden then breathinge vpon the childe, or anoylynge, which are reiect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as evill. It muſt needs com nearer to theſe, then it doth to Baptim which is commaunded.</note> but doth come many degrees neerer to the Evil then to the Good. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ther can be no miſticall Rite of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion indifferent.</p>
               <p n="16">16 An Evill Ceremonie of Religion being therefore onely Evill becauſe it is forbidden of God: A good Ceremonie
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:6727:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> of religion is therfore onely a good Cere<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mony becauſe it is commaunded of God: and that muſt be an indifferent ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie that is neither forbidden nor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded: But all ceremonies in religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that are not good, are evill, and there<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore there are no indifferent Ceremonies of Religion.</p>
               <p n="17">17 As no man by his ſole will, can make that ceremonie good in divyne worſhipp that God forbiddeth to be done their in, or make that Evill that God commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to be done therin. So can he not make that which is but indifferent to be Good: for he cannot make that to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded of God, that is forbidden of God, that (though it be not forbidden) is not commaunded: If therefore what Ceremonie of religion ſoeuer is good, be commaunded of God, and if every Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonie of religion ought to be good, &amp; if whatſoeuer ceremonie is commaund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of God is not Indifferent. Hence it wil followe: that no Ceremonie of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:6727:14"/> is indifferent.</p>
               <p n="18">18 Thus much of actions indifferent hauyng reference to God. Thoſe actions of man are indifferent in reſpect of a mans ſelfe, or his neighbour, that being committed, bring neither morall hurt nor good vnto him ſelfe or them. For thoſe actions are Evill to the doer, and ſuch as hurt his ſoule: that are a meanes of bringing either vpon himſelfe or vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his neighbour any evill forbidden. And thoſe actions are good to his ſoule, that are a meanes of affecting with any Good commaunded, him-ſelfe or his Neighbour.</p>
               <p n="19">19 Whatſoeuer therefore doeing a man no Good is a meanes either to<note n="e" place="margin">But we ſhalbe readie to proue, that ſuch is the lawe that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires theſe Ce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>remonies.</note> take fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a man any good thing that God hath freely graunted vnto him, as life, health libertie, name, honeſtie, pietie, &amp;c. Or to bring vpon a man that evill: that God otherwiſe with houldeth from him, that cannot be indifferent.</p>
               <p n="20">20 All ſuch humaine lawes therefore,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:6727:15"/> that<note n="f" place="margin">Much more thos Lawes tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> lay greater penalties vpon the omiſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i-of ſome Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, then the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of the greateſt good: or comiſſion of the groſſeſt euill and as doe the Canons &amp; lawes that requyre theſe Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies.</note> vpon any penalties, binde m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to thoſe things that are confeſſed indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fferent, which are ſuch things as God hath left to the free libertie of man to doe or not to<note n="g" place="margin">This hindreth not but that the Magiſtrat may and ought (yf it be for the good of the common weale) co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund fiſhe dayes, and ſuch lik, the neg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lect whereof, may doe much hurt, and the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation much good, for in ſuch caſes eatinge of fiſh and fleſh is not a Thing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, but that which men ſtand bound ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to for beare to doe accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to the Civill Lawes of Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates.</note> doe: is a deprivyng of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of that libertie that God hath grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; therfore ſuch a lawe <hi>is</hi> neither good nor indifferent, But evill to the ſoule of him that enacteth it, though not of him that obeyeth it. For it is no indifferencie in any man to take that away from a man that God hath freely given vnto him.</p>
               <p n="21">21 All Morall actions, of men that are good or evill, are either private, or com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon and publike. The common and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke, are either Domeſticall, Politicall, or Eccleſiaſticall. Actions alſo in their Indifferencie may vary accordinge to their diuers references to theſe.</p>
               <p n="22">22 A private Good or Euill action, is that which affecteth with good or Evill onely a mans owne perſon that doth it, and which ſpreadeth not to the Good or
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:6727:15"/> hurt of any other (except ſecondarely &amp; by accident) as he that eateth and drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth) doth himſelfe onely good properly: Though ſecondarely and by accident, he may, in that ſtrenght he receaueth, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by doe his family or the common wealth good.</p>
               <p n="23">23 That action is Indifferent in reſpect of a mans private ſelfe, that doth his owne priuate Perſon no wayes any good or hurt.</p>
               <p n="24">24 Thoſe Domeſticall, Politicall, Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall actions, are good, or evill, that tend to the good or hurt of a family, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, or Church, and thoſe are indifferent, that being done doe bringe neither good nor hurt, or as much good as hurt vnto any of the ſaide ſocieties.</p>
               <p n="25">25 That may be good, evill, or indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, to a private perſon as he is a priuat perſon, that is not ſo vnto a Family, Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth or Church, or vnto him, as he is a member, of all or any of them.</p>
               <p n="26">26 That may be Indifferent to be done
<pb facs="tcp:6727:16"/> by a Familie, or the Commen wealth as it is ſuch, That is evill and not indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, to be don by a Church. That may be indifferent to one member of a Houſe Church, or commenwealth, that is not Indifferent to another<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that may be law full or Indifferent for the Church to doe in one place and at ſome one time, that is vnlawefull in another place and at another time</p>
               <p n="27">27 All which premiſes or the moſt of them being graunted, it will eaſilie appeare to any that can rightlie applie theſe principles and generall aſſertions that the Cerimonies in preſent contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie in our Church are not (as is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by the forces of them) meerly Indifferent<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but either excellent parts of our religion or notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous parts of ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <closer>
               <date>APRILL. 12</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="summary">
            <pb facs="tcp:6727:16"/>
            <head>Summa Summae.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>THE PRELATES TO THE</hi> Afflicted Miniſters in this Realme.</head>
               <p>ALL thoſe that wilfully refuſe to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey the King in things Indifferent, and to conforme them ſelues to the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the church authorized by him, not contrarie to the word of God, are ſciſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maticks enimies to the Kings Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and State, and not to be tolerated in Church or commenwealth.</p>
               <p>But you doe wilfully refuſe to obey the King in things indifferent and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme your ſelues to the orders of the Church authoriſed by him not contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to the word of God Ergo</p>
               <p>You are Sciſmaticks Enimies to the Kings Supremacy &amp; the State,<note place="margin">Let them proue this aſſumption; but by one Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and we will yeald. But it is to be noted That the Prelats ſtill take all things co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tained therein as graun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted and without queſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on, where as we haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and offer to proue the contra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye.</note> and not to be tolerated in Church or Common wealth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>THE AFFLICTED</hi> MINI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, to the Prelates.</head>
               <p>All thos that freely &amp; willingly ꝓforme vnto the King and State, all Obedience
<pb facs="tcp:6727:17"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6727:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6727:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> not onely in thinges neceſſary, but <hi>Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fferent</hi> commanded by lawe. And that haue been alwayes readie to conforme the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to every order of the Church, authorized by him, not contrarie to the word of God, are free from all Sciſme, Frendes to the Kings Supremacie, and to the State, and vnworthy in this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to be moleſted in Church or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wealth.</p>
               <p>But<note n="e" place="margin">This Treatiſe: &amp; other bookes lately written, and exhibited to authoritie, doe proue the Aſſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> their is none of vs that is depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued or ſuſpended from our miniſtry, but hath ever ben readie, freely and willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to performe vnto the King and State all obedience, not only in things neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie but Indifferent, requyered by Lawe, And to conforme our ſelues to every Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Church authoriſed by him not contrary to the word of God. Ergo.</p>
               <p>We are all free from Sciſme, Frends to the Kings Supremacie and the State, and moſt vnworthy of ſuch moleſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Church and Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, as now wee ſuſtaine.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6727:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
